Chimpanzees, human beings’ closest animal relatives, share up to 98% of our genes.
黑猩猩是与人类亲缘关系最近的动物，它们和我们共有的基因多达98%。
Yet humans and chimpanzees lead very different lives.
然而，人类和黑猩猩过着大不相同的生活。
Fewer than 300,000 wild chimpanzees live in a few forested corners of Africa today, while humans have colonized every corner of the globe.
如今，野生黑猩猩不到30万只，生活在非洲少数几处森林覆盖的角落，而人类已经在全球每一个角落定居下来。
At more than 7 billion, human population dwarfs that of nearly all other mammals—despite our physical weaknesses.
人类人口超过70亿，让几乎所有其他哺乳动物的数量都相形见绌——尽管我们身体上存在种种弱点。
What could account for our species’ incredible evolutionary successes?
我们这个物种在进化上取得了惊人的成功，原因可能是什么呢？
One obvious answer is our big brains.
一个显而易见的答案是：我们的大脑很大。
It could be that our raw intelligence gave us an unprecedented ability to think outside the box, innovating solutions to thorny problems as people migrated across the globe.
可能是我们纯粹的智力赋予了我们前所未有的能力，使我们能够跳出思维定式，在人类向全球各地迁徙的过程中，为棘手的问题想出创新的解决办法。
But a growing number of cognitive scientists and anthropologists are rejecting that explanation.
但越来越多的认知科学家和人类学家正在否定这种解释。
They think that, rather than making our living as innovators, we survive and thrive precisely because we don’t think for ourselves.
他们认为，我们并不是靠创新谋生的；我们之所以能够生存并兴旺发达，恰恰是因为我们不独立思考。
Instead, people cope with challenging climates and ecological contexts by carefully copying others.
相反，人们是通过仔细模仿他人来应对严酷的气候和生态环境的。
In a famous study, psychologists Victoria Horner and Andrew Whiten showed two groups of test subjects—children and chimpanzees—a mechanical box with a treat inside.
在一项著名的研究中，心理学家维多利亚·霍纳和安德鲁·怀滕向两组受试者——儿童和黑猩猩——展示了一个机械盒子，盒子里放着一份奖励。
In one condition, the box was opaque, while in the other it was transparent.
在一种实验条件下，盒子不透明，而在另一种条件下，盒子是透明的。
The experimenters demonstrated how to open the box to retrieve the treat, but they also included the irrelevant step of tapping on the box with a stick.
实验人员演示了如何打开盒子取出奖励，但也加入了一个无关的步骤：用一根棍子轻敲盒子。
Oddly, the children carefully copied all the steps to open the box, even when they could see that the stick had no practical effect.
奇怪的是，即使能看出那根棍子并没有实际作用，孩子们也仔细地模仿了打开盒子的所有步骤。
That is, they copied irrationally: Instead of doing only what was necessary to get their reward, children slavishly imitated every action they’d witnessed.
也就是说，他们的模仿是不理性的：孩子们并不是只做获得奖励所必需的事，而是亦步亦趋地模仿了自己看到过的每一个动作。
Of course, that study only included three- and four-year-olds.
当然，那项研究只纳入了三四岁的孩子。
But additional research has shown that older children and adults are even more likely to mindlessly copy others’ actions, and infants are less likely to over-imitate—that is, to precisely copy even impractical actions.
但更多研究已经表明，年龄更大的儿童和成年人不假思索地模仿他人动作的可能性还要更大，而婴儿过度模仿的可能性则更小——所谓过度模仿，就是连没有实际用处的动作也精确地照搬。
By contrast, chimpanzees in the study only over-imitated in the opaque condition.
相比之下，那项研究中的黑猩猩只在盒子不透明的条件下过度模仿。
In the transparent condition—where they saw that the stick was mechanically useless—they ignored that step entirely.
在盒子透明的条件下，它们看出那根棍子对盒子的机关毫无作用，便完全忽略了那一步。
Other research has since supported these findings.
此后，又有其他研究支持了这些发现。
When it comes to copying, chimpanzees are more rational than human children or adults.
在模仿这件事上，黑猩猩比人类的儿童和成年人都更理性。
Where does the seemingly irrational human preference for over-imitation come from?
人类偏爱过度模仿，这种看似不理性的偏好从何而来？
Anthropologist Joseph Henrich points out that people around the world rely on technologies that are often so complex that no one can learn them rationally.
人类学家约瑟夫·亨里奇指出，世界各地的人们所依赖的技术往往复杂到没有人能凭理性学会。
Instead, people must learn them step by step, trusting in the wisdom of more experienced elders and peers.
相反，人们必须一步一步地学习这些技术，信赖经验更丰富的长辈和同辈的智慧。
So the next time you hear someone arguing passionately that everyone should embrace nonconformity and avoid imitating others, you might laugh a little bit.
所以，下次再听到有人慷慨激昂地主张人人都应该崇尚特立独行、避免模仿他人，你或许会觉得有点好笑。
We’re not chimpanzees, after all.
毕竟，我们不是黑猩猩。